What if I just dug a really, really deep
hole? That's what the USSR did right
here. That hole is 12.2 km or 7.6 mi
deep. That makes it deeper than the
Mariana Trench. It's deeper than Mount
Everest is tall. The USSR dug it
starting in 1970. It was part of a race
to see who could retrieve a sample from
the Earth's mantle first. Kind of a
space race, but the opposite. The United
States only reached 600 ft before
pulling funding, but the USSR kept going
for 20 years. They made it about a third
of the way through Earth's crust before
the temperature got a lot hotter than
they expected. Their drill bits started
melting. The rock was so hot, it was
like plastic. But along the way they
invented all kinds of drilling and
scientific equipment that we still use
today. They found fossils of organisms
dating back 2 billion years and
discovered that there was water much
deeper than previously thought. It's
crazy though that the deepest hole
humanity has ever dug is only 0.2% of
the way to the middle of the Earth.
There's so much that we still don't know
about our own planet. If you like
optimistic science and tech stories,
follow for more.